Start. Okay, good morning. Today is May 4th, May the 4th be
with you. It's the 19th of אייר, Iyar, it's the 34th day
of the עומר, Omer, and we'll pick up towards the bottom of
כ עמוד ב. Kaf Amud Bet. Today's דף Daf will be כ
א, Kaf Aleph, and we're in the discussions of hand washing and
foot washing for the כהנים Cohanim
during their עבודה, Avodah, before the עבודה, Avodah, various stages in their
process.
Sorry, I think I lost the place, but we're going from where
it says איבעיא להו Iba'ya Lehu like about twelve lines from the
bottom of כ עמוד ב. Kaf Amud Bet.
Okay, so we're picking up sort of a new question but within
the same themes. The גמרא Gemara asks, איבעיא להו טומאה מהו שתועיל
קידוש ידים ורגלים? Iba'ya Lehu Tumah mahu sheto'il Kiddush Yadayim V'Raglayim? So
what about in a case of a כהן Kohen who in the
middle of the עבודה Avodah or while in process becomes טמא? Tamei?
So at that point, would we say that you have to, does
the purification that they have to go through going to the מקוה
Mikvah serve,
qualify for hand and foot washing or does it have to have
the hand and foot washing done separately? Okay, so it's a bit
of a strange way of saying
it, טומאה Tumah isn't תועיל, to'il, the going to the מקוה Mikvah
will be תועיל to'il for that. It's a little bit of a
strange way, when I first saw the question I was like, wait,
what? But then you have to kind of
look at רש"י.
Rashi.
So אם תמצי לומר יציאה לא פסלה דגברא חזי אבל הכא דגברא
לא חזי אסוחי מסח דעתיה? Im timtzei lomar Yetziah la pasla d'gavra
chazi aval hacha d'gavra lo chazi asuchi masech datei?
Do we suggest that what's a problem for קידוש ידים
ורגלים Kiddush Yadayim V'Raglayim where you would have to wash your hands
and feet again is in a case where you,
well actually leaving the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash we say is not
such a problem because okay, you can still maintain consciousness of what
you're touching with your hands and your feet and you're not going
to be distracted. So יציאה לא פסלה, Yetziah la pasla,
if leaving the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash does not פסל pasel your
hand and foot washing, as you don't have to do it again
because you're a גברא חזי, gavra chazi, the כהן Kohen is still
a person who could do the עבודה. Avodah. That's one possibility. But
this case, because a person has become טמא, Tamei, he's not able
to do the עבודה. Avodah. So the fact that he's totally removed
from the ability to do the עבודה Avodah serves as a heightened
sense of distractibility or distraction because he's not focused on going back
to do the עבודה. Avodah. So because he's טמא, Tamei, he's like,
okay, I'm not going to do the עבודה Avodah anymore, so he
doesn't have that consciousness. אודלמא כיון דהדר חזי דקלי ולא מסח דעתיה?
Odilma kevan d'hadar
chazi daklei v'lo masech datei?
Doesn't if he becomes טמא, Tamei, doesn't he usually need הערב שמש?
ha'erev shemesh?
Right, where the גמרא Gemara is going to raise that question. In
which case then he wouldn't be able to do it anyway. Okay,
but there are possibilities, so the גמרא Gemara is exactly getting to
that, which is what possibility of what if you became טמא Tamei
right very in the late afternoon so that the length of time,
you could go to the
מקוה Mikvah quickly, the sun will set and then you'll do the
עבודה Avodah of the night or whatever. Right. So it's a still
a possibility that someone could become טמא Tamei and then become טהור
Tahor in relatively quick succession. But generally, the concern is exactly what
Michael is saying, which is that even the length of time is
going to be an extended period of time.
But we say that also about going out of the עזרה. Azarah.
I mean in minimally you need קידוש ידים ורגלים, Kiddush Yadayim V'Raglayim,
you may need to be you know...
Right, but here יציאה, Yetziah, right, so the point of יציאה, Yetziah,
the יציאה Yetziah sense is that okay, יציאה Yetziah maybe is a
shorter window of time, but in case of יציאה Yetziah you're also
you're a גברא חזי, gavra chazi, you're still suitable to do the
עבודה. Avodah. In the case of, so what is it that causes
the היסח הדעת? hesach hadaat? Is it the length of time of
the interruption or is it the circumstances under which the interruption takes
place that whether or not you're going to lose your consciousness or
your mindfulness of of this state that you're in? אודלמא כיון דהדר
חזי דקלי ולא מסח דעתיה. Odilma kevan d'hadar chazi daklei v'lo masech
datei.
So maybe because you know the fact that he could go to
the מקוה Mikvah is still not going to serve as a problem
to be an interruption for him to require him to have קידוש
ידים ורגלים Kiddush Yadayim V'Raglayim again. So that's our question. So תא
שמע קידש ידיו ורגליו ונטמא. Ta shema Kidush yadav v'raglav v'nitma. In
a case where a person had washed his hands and feet and
then they became טמא, Tamei, that is the hands, we have a
rabbinic rule that hands separate from the rest of the body can
become טמא, Tamei, touching various things that wouldn't necessarily make a person
as a whole טמא, Tamei, but nonetheless we say the hands are
טמאים. tme'im. So the solution to that is either is usually immersing
your hands independently into the מקוה, Mikvah, just the hands. So here
the ברייתא Braisa says מטבילן ואין צריך לקדש. matbilan v'ein tzarich lekadesh.
You can immerse your hands in the מקוה, Mikvah, but you don't
have to wash them from the כיור. Kiyor. נטמאו ידיו לא מיבעיא
לן כי מיבעיא לן נטמא כל גופו. Nitma'u yadav lo miba'ya lan
ki miba'ya lan nitma kol gufo. No, so that's not the question
that was actually being asked, because hands that are טמא tamei is
an easy fix. It's you can just dip them in the מקווה,
Mikvah, so it's not going to be such a problem.
But what about are we saying that every כהן Kohen that starts
out in the morning, instead of doing קידוש ידים ורגלים, Kiddush yadayim
v'raglayim, could just טובל tovel his hands in a מקווה? Mikvah?
It serves a different purpose because if it
works for two it really should work for one.
No, because at that point the point is that for the עבודה
avoda you need קידוש ידים ורגלים Kiddush yadayim v'raglayim from the כיור,
Kiyor, ורחצו ידיהם ורגליהם ולא ימותו, v'rachatzu yedeihem v'ragleihem v'lo yamutu, right?
So even though, but don't they have to also be טובל tovel
in the מקווה Mikvah every morning before going?
I would presume, I don't know why you would go to the
מקווה Mikvah in the morning. I would imagine you would go to
the מקווה Mikvah in the afternoon of the day before just in
case whatever. Didn't they go every day anyway? But I'm not even
sure, maybe it's unnecessary if they're still טהורים, tehorim, it doesn't matter.
You know.
So anyway, כל גופו. col gufo. So כי מיבעיא לן נטמא כל
גופו. ki mibayan nitma col gufo. So the question that had been
asked, the איבעיא להו ibaya lehu question, was about נטמא כל גופו,
nitma col gufo, the person's whole body became טמא. tamei. So
כל גופו? col gufo? דאיבעי ליה מאבד הערב שמש. de-iba'i leih me-abad
He'rev Shemesh. This was Michael's point that wait a second, if a
person's whole body became טמא, tamei, that is the person actually became
טמא, tamei, you need to go to the מקווה Mikvah usually, let's
say in the afternoon, you'll need הערב שמש. He'rev Shemesh. You need
to wait until the sunset to be fully טהור. tahor. In the
period between going to the מקווה Mikvah and sunset, a person would
be considered a טבול יום, tvul yom, which is a fascinating intermediate
status but is not fully fully טהור. tahor. So during that period
because you have to wait until הערב שמש, He'rev Shemesh, אסוחי מסח
דעתיה, asochei masach da'atei, maybe we'll say that that length of time
of just waiting around is going to cause him to have this
הסח הדעת hessech hadaat and he's going to have to wash his
hands again. So כגון דאיטמי סמוך לשקיעת החמה. kegon de'itmei samuch lishki'as
hachamah. So the גמרא Gemara suggests no, the question was asked specifically
about a case where a person became טמא tamei soon before sunset.
He became טמא tamei in the late afternoon, quickly went to the
מקווה Mikvah in the late afternoon before sunset, and then the sunset.
So it's actually could be only five minutes between the period of
time when the person became טמא tamei and when they become טהור
tahor again in such a case. And then the question is does
he have to do קידוש? Kiddush? And then the question would be
because it was such a short length of time, do they need
to wash their hands again, hands and feet again, or do we
say that the length of time that they were טמא tamei is
not enough of a problem to have caused הסח הדעת? hessech hadaat?
So that's the question. We clarified the question, right? We still don't
have the answer to the question. So the גמרא Gemara now says
תא שמע. ta shema. Yeah.
I'm a little bit confused about the hands and the feet as
opposed to the rest of the body. Right. So when he goes
in the מקווה Mikvah that's his whole body.
That's purifying it, that's making him טהור. tahor. He was טמא tamei
and now he's טהור. tahor. Right.
So now does he still have to do his hands and feet?
That's our question.
That's the question.
The question, exactly. So the question is in such a case does
the fact so we say טומאה, tuma, that is going to the
מקווה Mikvah because you were
טמא, tamei, מהו שתועיל לקידוש ידים ורגלים? mahu she-to'il le-Kiddush yadayim v'raglayim?
Does that count for hand and foot washing or not? So that's
the standing question and we've narrowed the scope of the question to
be specifically in a case where the person became טמא tamei soon
before sunset so that the time window that we're talking about is
a narrow window because otherwise if it were a very lengthy time
we would be more concerned about הסח הדעת hessech hadaat and then
the question wouldn't even get off the ground. Okay. So now another
suggestion from a from another ברייתא. braisa. תא שמע. ta shema. פרה.
Para. In the case of פרה, Para, in the case of preparing
for the פרה אדומה, Para Aduma, which is a sort of a
strange kind of עבודה avoda because in some sense it really is
an עבודה avoda of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, has to be
done by the כהן, Kohen, maybe even the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
has to be done with the בגדים, bgadim, it has to be
done by people who are טהורים, tehorim, etc., etc. At the same
time, it's done outside the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. It's not exactly
an עבודה, avoda, it's not exactly a קרבן. korban. There are all
these kind of things that make the פרה אדומה Para Aduma this
strange intermediate kind of a case. So in the case of פרה,
Para, רבי חייא ברבי יוסף Rabbi Chiya berabbi Yosef אמר amar מקדש
בכלי שרת בפנים. mekadesh bikli shares bifnim. A person could wash his
hands and feet using a כלי שרת kli shares inside the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash ויוצא, veyotzei, and then leave the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash to go to הר הזיתים Har HaZeisim to do the to
do the פרה אדומה. Para Aduma. That is the and the the
gap in between is not a problem. We're not concerned about הסח
הדעת hessech hadaat in the in the intermediate time.
We just mentioned that פרה אדומה. Para Aduma. Right. It's it's going
to come up.
It's a class because it's one of these paradigmatic examples because it's
so unique and so.
So we always bring up we then we can say you never
learn, you can't learn anything from it.
Right, because it's so unique and so. So it has very it
can be compared to everything and often the comparison will be rejected.
ורבי יוחנן v'Rabbi Yochanan אמר amar אפילו בחוץ. afilu bachutz. You could
even wash your hands בחוץ, bachutz, outside the temple, ואפילו בכלי חול,
va-afilu b'kli chol, and even with not a כלי שרת, kli shares,
just a regular cup. That is, the act of hand washing is
not part of the עבודה avoda because the פרה אדומה Para Aduma
is not an עבודה. avoda.
Well probably if you're בחוץ bachutz it has to not be a
כלי שרת.
kli shares. Right, presumably if it's בחוץ. bachutz. But it's saying אפילו
בחוץ אפילו בכלי חול afilu bachutz afilu b'kli chol kind of go
hand in hand, ואפילו במקירה של חרס, va-afilu b'makeira shel cheres, even
this sort of very cheap, very low quality kind of earthenware bowls.
Like our little plastic wash basins?
Right, the things that we use for hand washing. That is, it
would be like hand washing that we
do.
Look at that one
doesn't
really present a problem if our question is the time duration between
washing and doing the עבודה. avodah. Right. So the fact that they
let you...
it's still some length of time.
But no, you can go to the מקוה mikveh and one second
later do the פרה אדומה. parah adumah.
Well that's exactly the... so the challenge to this is that פרה
אדומה parah adumah was done דוקא davka with people who are... with
the כהנים kohanim who are טבול יום. tevul yom. We're going to
see exactly that's the next line in the גמרא. Gemara. הפרה דטמויי
מטמינן לה, Ha'parah detamuyei metaminan lah, but in the case of פרה,
parah, the כהן kohen who burns the פרה, parah, they would make
him טמא. tamei. דתנן, De'tenan, this is one of the most interesting
משניות mishnayot in פרה Parah and it has become a source of
much polemic debate in recent years. מטמאים היו הכהן השורף את הפרה,
Metammim hayu ha'kohen ha'soref et ha'parah, they would make the כהן kohen
who was going to burn the פרה parah טמא, tamei, ומטבילין אותו
u'matbilin oto and then take him to the מקוה mikveh immediately, להוציא
מלבן של צדוקים שהיו אומרים במעורב שמש היתה נעשית lehotzi milibam shel
Tzadukim she'hayu omrim be'me'orev shemesh hayetah na'asit
because the רבנים rabbanim and the צדוקים Tzadukim disagreed, פרושים Perushim and
צדוקים Tzadukim disagreed about whether or not a טבול יום tevul yom
is טהור tahor enough to burn the פרה. parah. So on the
one hand we have so many stringencies and strictures by the פרה
אדומה parah adumah to make sure it's done in the highest levels
of טהרה, taharah, even to the extent that the normal gradations of
שלישי shlishi and רביעי revi'i by טומאה tumah are extended even further
for פרה, parah, there may be חמישי chamishi or other kinds of
much farther levels of טומאה, tumah, and the children who were involved
in the production of the פרה parah and the drawing the water
for the פרה parah were born on a platform in ירושלים Yerushalayim
to make sure that they would never become טמא tamei in their
whole lives and things like that. They built the bridge. Wait, they
build the bridges and all of... the bridge has to be a
double bridge. So there's so many reasons why we take extreme stringency
about the טהרה taharah of the פרה parah process, and at the
same time we wanted to stick one to the צדוקים Tzadukim to
prove that they're wrong, so we make the כהן kohen טמא tamei
and then we take him to the מקוה mikveh so that he'll
be a טבול יום. tevul yom. So that's what this משנה mishnah
says, ומטבילין אותו להוציא מלבן של צדוקים u'matbilin oto lehotzi milibam shel
Tzadukim to prove the צדוקים Tzadukim wrong, שהיו אומרים במעורב שמש היתה
נעשית she'hayu omrim be'me'orev shemesh hayetah na'asit because the צדוקים Tzadukim held
that the פרה אדומה parah adumah must be done with such a
high level of טהרה taharah that even a טבול יום tevul yom
is not allowed to do it. So it's fascinating it becomes a
distinction between and that's one of the differences also for the פרה
אדומה parah adumah that it's not really an עבודה avodah because a
טבול יום tevul yom isn't allowed to bring a קרבן korban or
to do other things in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash because he's
still טמא. tamei. But for the פרה אדומה parah adumah he's considered
טהור tahor enough for the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. So שמע מינה
לא פסלה בה טומאה. shema mina lo paslah bah tumah. So you
could infer from the case of פרה אדומה parah adumah from that
משנה mishnah that if they were מטמא metammei this כהן kohen and
they would take him to the מקוה mikveh and then he would
do the פרה אדומה parah adumah and that was all after he
had washed his hands and feet in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash,
then it must be that טומאה tumah is not an interruption, הסח
הדעת, hesech hadaat, for your קידוש ידים ורגלים. kiddush yadayim ve'raglayim. So
that sounds like a pretty good proof. Okay. But as people pointed
out שאני פרה הואיל וטבול יום לא פסיל בה. shani parah ho'il
ve'tevul yom lo pasil bah. So the distinction that we can make
about פרה אדומה parah adumah is that it has this special dispensation
or special leniency that because a טבול יום tevul yom is allowed
to do it that that we can't learn from there to the
normal rules of the עבודה. avodah. So אי הכי למה לי דמקדש
כעין עבודה בעינן. ei hachi lamah li demikadesh ke'ein avodah bayinan.
So why would we say דמקדש, demikadesh, why do you have to
wash your hands and feet at all for the פרה אדומה? parah
adumah? And the answer is כעין עבודה בעינן, ke'ein avodah bayinan, you
have to do it like the עבודה. avodah. And again it's kind
of walking this line. It's like the עבודה avodah but it's not
like the עבודה. avodah. It's a little bit like the עבודה avodah
but not in a hundred percent of its ways. Could spend a
lot of time on פרה אדומה. parah adumah.
I hear there's a whole מסכת masechet about it.
There is a whole מסכת masechet about it, there's no גמרא Gemara
about it, but fourteen פרקים prakim there's a lot of material.
I have never met anyone who's actually learned that מסכת. masechet.
I've learned it probably a dozen times. Oh really? Wow! I'm... I
have a soft spot in my heart for מסכת פרה. Masechet Parah.
Hey, another time. When we get to it in the דף היומי
Daf Yomi then we'll have a שיעור shiur on it. Okay. איבעיא
להו. iba'ya lehu. On the day between the last דף daf of
נדה Niddah and the first דף daf of ברכות Berakhot we could
learn טהרות. Toharot. Okay. איבעיא להו מהו לקדש ידיו ורגליו בכיור? iba'ya
lehu mahu le'kadesh yadav ve'raglav be'kiyor?
So are you allowed, so this is a question, are you allowed
to instead of pouring the water from the כיור kiyor onto your
hands and feet, what about dipping your hands and feet into the
כיור? kiyor? This is what רש״י Rashi clarifies that otherwise it's not
even a question.
That sounds a little bit like spiteful.
It sounds it's like a little bit gross, right? You stick your
feet into the public water, right? The whole idea of a flowing
water faucet is that you don't get the dirty water on everybody
else. But anyway it's an interesting question because we have this distinction
between flowing water and stationary water. Immersion in water or or being
washed by the water. So that's part of this question. So מהו
לקדש ידיו ורגליו בכיור ממנו אמר רחמנא. mahu le'kadesh yadav ve'raglav be'kiyor
mimenu amar Rachmana. The Torah says you have to wash your hands
from from it ורחצו ידיהם ורגליהם Verachatzu yadeihem veragleihem ורחצו ממנו. Verachatzu
mimenu.
There are too many פסוקים. pesukim. It's so repetitive at the beginning
of כי תשא, Ki Tisa, right? את ידיהם ורגליהם בבואם אל אהל
מועד לשרת בקודש, et yadeihem veragleihem bevo'am el ohel mo'ed lesharet bakodesh,
right? ולא בתוכו. velo betocho.
So maybe you would say that means you can't put your hands
and feet into the כיור. kiyor. אודלמא, אפילו בתוכו, odlma afillu betocho,
right?
So do we learn this exclusion from the word ממנו mimenu or
not? That's the question. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak, רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak says תא
שמע, ta shma, you should learn from here: או שטבל
במי מערה ועבד עבודתו
פסולה.
o shetaval bemei me'arah ve'avad
avodato psulah.
So we haven't answered our questions. Which question? The previous question? No,
we said maybe you could learn from פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, we
rejected the comparison to פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. Right, so you don't
know. So we don't learn from פרה אדומה? Parah Adumah? Sounds like
if they had a proposed answer that was rejected, usually I imagine
that means that the answer is the opposite. If you can't bring
this good proof, or you're able to reject it, but it could
be left open. Sometimes some of these kinds of questions are left
open, and that's okay too.
תיקו. teiku. It doesn't say תיקו teiku either, it's just left unanswered.
But wouldn't that be because
תיקו teiku is an active acknowledgment that they decided not to resolve
the question or they never reached a resolution. Here it's sort of
a general...
do you have any sense of where...?
There's a מנחת חינוך Minchat Chinuch that made a statement when I
asked this on a previous just a few דפים dappim before where
they didn't make any decisions. He said they didn't even say תיקו,
teiku, meaning it was just clear.
Yeah, I'm not sure. In this kind of a case, I'm not
100% sure. I mean, the place to look would be like in
the ליקוטי הלכות Likutei Halachot of the חפץ חיים Chofetz Chaim or
to look in the רמב״ם Rambam and to try to get a
sense of what some of the ראשונים Rishonim say. I don't have
a gut feeling on this one, so I would want to look
at it a little bit more. Okay, so we have the next
question. איבעיא להו iba'u lehu מהו לקדש ידיו ורגליו בכיור, mahu lekadesh
yadav veraglav bekiyor, can you immerse your hands and feet into the
כיור? kiyor? ממנו אמר רחמנא ולא בתוכו, mimenu amar Rachmana velo betocho,
do we say that you have to wash it from the כיור
kiyor and not inside the כיור? kiyor? אודלמא odlma, אפילו בתוכו, afillu
betocho, or maybe you could even immerse into the כיור? kiyor? אמר
רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, רב נחמן בר
יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak says תא שמע: ta shma: או שטבל
במי מערה ועבד עבודתו פסולה. o shetaval bemei me'arah ve'avad avodato psulah.
So if you immerse in מי מערה, mei me'arah, in a מקוה
mikvah basically, water that's in a cave, in a well, ועבד עבודתו,
ve'avad avodato, and you went to do the עבודה, avoda, it's פסולה.
psulah. It sounds like immersing into מקוה mikvah water by itself is
not good enough to stand the place of קידוש ידים ורגלים. kidush
yadayim veraglayim. So
הקיור דומיא דמי מערה, ha'kiyor dumya d'mei me'arah, and the water in
the כיור kiyor is comparable to a cave water in that it's
stationary, that is immersing into it may not work, ועבד עבודתו כשרה,
ve'avad avodato kshira, but then in that case how you know could
you say that putting your hands and feet into the כיור kiyor
that would
work because... so no. מי מערה איצטריכא ליה. mei me'arah itztericha lei.
No, the reason why the משנה Mishnah mentions מי מערה mei me'arah
is to exclude something else. שלא תאמר כל גופו טובל בהן ידו
ורגלו לא כל שכן, shelo tomar kol gufo tovel bahen yado veraglo
lo kol sheken, because in order to prove to you the fact
that just because you can immerse in a מקוה mikvah in order
to make yourself טהור tahor does not mean that immersing your hands
and feet into something like a מקוה mikvah would make them מקודש
mekudash for the עבודה. avoda. The act of preparation for the עבודה
avoda has to be from the כיור, kiyor, has to be from
a כלי שרת, kli sharet, has to be in the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash for that intention, and so maybe that's what it comes
to exclude. It comes to exclude dipping your hands and feet into
a מקוה, mikvah, but dipping your hands and feet into the כיור
kiyor maybe it would work because you're actually using the כיור. kiyor.
So the attempted proof that רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak tried to bring from this ברייתא braita is not so dispositive.
אמרי רב חייא בר יוסף, Amri Rav Chiya bar Yosef, רב חייא
בר יוסף Rav Chiya bar Yosef says מי כיור נפסלין למתירין כמתירין
לאיברים כאיברים. mei kiyor nifsalin lematirin kematirin le'eivarim ke'eivarim. So we're getting
into now a bit of a new question and this is going
to be a bit of an extensive debate, we're going to have
a few different opinions here so we have to keep track a
little bit carefully,
which is when does the water that stays in the כיור kiyor
become פסול pasul for the next day? Because we have this whole
solution of cranking it into the underground hole so that it's immersed
in water overnight so that the water won't become פסול pasul because
otherwise if it would stay out overnight then they would have to
drain out all the water every day and refill it, right? So
it's much more convenient to use the crank when it's hard in
a dry area. It's hard in a dry... in ירושלים Yerushalayim you
prefer to save the water as much as possible. So right, there
you go, nice conservation pitch.
So the opinion of רב חייא בר יוסף Rav Chiya bar Yosef
is מי כיור נפסלין למתירין כמתירין. mei kiyor nifsalin lematirin kematirin. מתירין
matirin here referring to קרבנות korbanot that are brought during the day.
It comes to provide a מתיר, matir, I guess here the word
מתיר matir is like it permits you, so it's in a case
of someone who had an obligation to bring a bring a חיוב.
chiyuv. bringing a קרבן, korban, that bringing his קרבן korban exempts them
from their obligation. So if you are doing the עבודה avodah of
the daytime, that is מתירים, matirin, you're doing normal עבודות, avodot, then
the water from the כיור kiyor will become פסול pasul for you
כמתירים kematirin at the time when those קרבנות korbanot become פסול, pasul,
that is, sunset. לאיברים כאיברים. Leivarim keivarim. And if you're going to
do the עבודה avodah of the איברים eivarim of burning the fats
and burning the limbs on the מזבח mizbeach overnight, then the water
is considered to become פסול pasul in the morning at sunrise. That
is, for the עבודות avodot of the day, the water becomes פסול
pasul at sunset. For the עבודות avodot of the night, it becomes
פסול pasul at sunrise. Okay, that's the opinion of רבי חייא בר
יוסף, Rabbi Chiya bar Yosef, okay? So far so good? So he
has two different time points, sunset and sunrise. רב חסדא אמר אף
למתירים אין נפסלין אלא בעמוד השחר כאיברים. Rav Chisda amar af lematirin
ein nifsalin ela be'amud hashachar keivarim. And Rav Chisda's position is that
the water only becomes disqualified at sunrise, not at sunset. ורבי יוחנן
אמר כיור כיון ששקעו שוב אין מעלהו. VeRabbi Yochanan amar kiyor keivan
sheshik'u shuv ein ma'alehu. Rabbi Yochanan says once they immerse the כיור
kiyor in the water in the hole, which they presumably would do
in the evening,
then שוב אין מעלהו, shuv ein ma'alehu, you can't take it out
again until the next morning. That sounds like Rabbi Yochanan's position is
that if the water would be left out at night at any
point during the night, that it would be disqualified.
למימרא דלעבודת לילה נמי, Lememra de'avodat laila nami, that is, for עבודת
לילה avodat laila it becomes disqualified. What?
It was there for a little bit in the night, so it's
not?
No, because if you put it down in the hole, says שוב
אין מעלהו, shuv ein ma'alehu, you don't take it out until the
next morning, because if you take it out now at night.
No, but I'm saying if I want to do something in the
night? Yeah.
Then you have to wash your hands before sunset.
No, but I'm saying why can't I do it now?
Because they put the כיור kiyor away already. שוב אין מעלהו.
shuv
ein ma'alehu.
So maybe, okay, we're going to get to it, but maybe Rabbi
Yochanan doesn't think that it becomes פסול pasul at that point, but
they made a גזירה gezeirah about it. It's a little bit of
a we're going to get to it. Okay. So, but at least
so far we have three different opinions about when does the water
become פסול: pasul: basically sunset and sunrise, or just sunrise, or something
in the evening, maybe sunset-ish.
Okay.
למימרא דלעבודת לילה נמי חזי. Lememra de'avodat laila nami chazi. והאמר רבי
אסי אמר רבי יוחנן, Veha'amar Rabbi Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan, didn't Rabbi
Assi quote Rabbi Yochanan saying משמיה דאילפא, mishmei deIlfa, quoting אילפא? Ilfa?
אילפא Ilfa we know from גמרא Gemara in תענית, Taanit, that אילפא
Ilfa was that Rabbi Yochanan was invited to come back to the
בית המדרש Beis Hamidrash and אילפא Ilfa didn't hear so he went
to become a rich businessman, but he
still had all his תורה.
Torah. But he still had a lot of תורה Torah and he
said אילפא's Ilfa main strength according to that סוגיא sugya is that
every ברייתא braita he could connect to a משנה. mishna. That is
every teaching in the ברייתא braita he could show you how it
really could be learned out from the משניות mishnayot as well. So
he had great faith in the editing of the משניות. mishnayot.
Okay, so what did Rabbi Yochanan say? So the point is that
this is going to prove as a contradiction to Rabbi Yochanan's position.
כיור שלא שקעו מאתמול, Kiyor shelo shika'o me'etmol, if they did not
put the כיור kiyor into its hole from the evening, מקדש ממנו
לעבודת לילה. mikadesh mimeno la'avodat laila. You could still wash your hands
throughout the night. If they didn't put it away, you could still
use it. ולמחר אינו מקדש. Ulemachar eino mikadesh. And tomorrow, that is,
once it becomes day again, you couldn't use it. That sounds like
Rabbi Yochanan's position is that it becomes disqualified at sunrise. That would
be in accordance with Rav Chisda. So the second version of Rabbi
Yochanan seems to not have a מחלוקת machlokes with Rav Chisda. So
now we say מאי אינו מעלהו? Mai eino ma'alehu? So why does
Rabbi Yochanan say you're not allowed to raise it up again during
the night? So נמי דקאמר לעבודת יום. nami deka'amar le'avodat yom. Maybe
you should say the same applies for the עבודות avodot during the
day as well. אבל לעבודת לילה חזי. Aval le'avodat laila chazi. But
if it wasn't taken out, it still would be suitable to be
used for עבודת לילה, avodat laila, that is, if it was left
out that you could use it for the עבודה avodah of the
night, which is what the second version of Rabbi Yochanan said. אי
הכי,
Ei
hachi, if that's so, היינו דרבי חייא בר יוסף. hainu deRabbi Chiya
bar Yosef. So if that's the case, then Rabbi Yochanan is just
saying the position of Rabbi Chiya bar Yosef, that is, for the
עבודות avodot of the daytime it becomes disqualified at night, that is,
at sunset, and for the עבודות avodot of the night it becomes
disqualified at sunrise in the day. So why is Rabbi Yochanan treated
as a third position if he agrees with Rabbi Chiya bar Yosef?
That is, the second version of Rabbi Yochanan seems not to be
any different either from Rav Chisda or from Rabbi Chiya bar Yosef.
So what is his position actually? So איכא בינייהו גזירת שיקוע. Ika
beiniyahu gezeirat shikua. No, the difference is not about post facto what's
the consequence of whether or not you left the water out, but
גזירת שיקוע. gezeirat shikua. Rabbi Yochanan's teaching is the point that they
had a positive mandate to make sure that they should put away
the כיור kiyor in the evening, not that there's some problem with
it if it got left out. והאמר רבי יוחנן קידש ידיו לתרומת
הדשן למחר אין צריך לקדש שכבר קידש מתחילת עבודה. Veha'amar Rabbi Yochanan
kidesh yadav litrumat hadeshen lemachar ein tzarich lekadesh shekvar kidesh mitechilat avodah.
So,
and the position of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is if someone washes
his hands to do תרומת הדשן, Trumat Hadeshen, which started in the
middle of the
night—that is, so he washed his hands presumably in the beginning of
the night or perhaps even in the afternoon. So he washed his
hands already to do תרומת הדשן למחר, Trumat Hadeshen l'machar, that is
for tomorrow's, for what would take place early in the morning or
right before sunrise. So אין צריך לקדש, ein tzarich l'kadesh, you don't
have to go back and wash your hands again, שכבר קידש מתחילת
עבודה. she'kvar kideish mit'chilat avoda. He already had started washing his hands
already from in the afternoon. Okay, so בשלמא לרבא דמוקים לה האי
כרבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. bishlama l'Rava d'mukeim la hai k'Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi
Shimon. So that all fits according to לרבא l'Rava who thinks that
the הלכה halacha is like רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi
Shimon, that's the opinion that we had already. That is what? רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון'ס Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon's position was
back there, which was that we say אין לילה אלא בקידוש. ein
layla ela b'kiddush. That you can't wash your hands at night, so
you have to do it during the day, right? So he would
have washed his hands in the afternoon or the previous day, he's
stayed up all night and he's going to do תרומת הדשן Trumat
Hadeshen now around midnight or around 2:00 in the morning and that's
okay, he doesn't have to wash his hands a second time. Okay,
however, הא כרבי. ha k'Rabbi. And this position seems to be like
רבי'ס Rabbi's position.
That is that if רבא Rava thinks the הלכה halacha is like
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon and then it's just
a מחלוקת, machloket, so fine. אלא לאביי, Ella l'Abaye, but אביי Abaye
דמוקים ליה כרבי, d'mukeim lei k'Rabbi, but אביי Abaye who holds the
הלכה halacha is like רבי Rabbi that nighttime serves as an interruption
for קידוש ידים ורגלים, kiddush yadayim v'raglayim, sunset and therefore you'd have
to wash your hands and feet again once the sun sets in
order to do the תרומת הדשן. Trumat Hadeshen. So קשיא, kashya, that's
a problem because it sounds like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan doesn't agree
with רבי'ס Rabbi's position. Okay, so קשיא דרבי אדרבי. kashya d'Rabbi ad'Rabbi.
It's also a challenge within רבי'ס Rabbi's position. So מאי שנא התם
דמשקליה ומאי שנא הכא דלא משקליה? mai shna hatam d'mishkalei u'mai shna
hacha d'lo mishkalei?
So why would there be a distinction in which cases did they
or did they not actually immerse the כיור kiyor in its hole
underground? דמסלק ליה והדר משקליה. d'misalek lei v'hadar mishkalei.
So maybe the case is a case where they had put it
away and they took it back out again and they put it
back, put it away again. So אי הכי למחר אינו מקדש? i
hachi l'machar eini m'kadesh? So if that's the case and you're telling
me fine, so someone washed his hands in the afternoon and now
he doesn't need to wash them again to do תרומת הדשן Trumat
Hadeshen in the middle of the
night, אמאי צריך לקדש? amai tzarich l'kadesh? למימרא דלא מתירין מחזי חזי,
L'memra d'lo matirin michzei chazi, since he was suitable to do the
עבודה avoda of the daytime for the מתירין מחזי חזי, matirin michzei
chazi, היינו דרב חסדא. hinu d'Rav Chisda.
And that's like רב חסדא'ס Rav Chisda's position. So then איכא בינייהו
מצוות שיקוע. ika beinihu mitzvat shiku'a. And the debate is only about
whether you actually have to put the כיור kiyor away at night.
So again, we've kind of gone through a lot of footwork here,
I know it's a bit dense, but the point is to say
the debate between רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and רב חסדא Rav Chisda
is not about whether the water becomes פסול pasul if it's left
out at night or the issues that it's somewhat connected to the
debate between רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon and רבי
Rabbi about whether sunset is going to be an interruption for קידוש
ידים ורגלים. kiddush yadayim v'raglayim. And it's connected more to the question
of whether there's a requirement גזרת שיקוע, gezeirat shiku'a, there was a
requirement made in the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash that they have to
put away the כיור kiyor at night or whether it's just, well
if you don't put it away, there'll be consequences so it's a
good idea to do it, but whether that was actually made mandatory
or not.
Okay, look at this רש"י Rashi here. That
the כיור kiyor must be kept submerged because we're concerned that if
it is raised, it might not be submerged again before daybreak.
Right, so maybe that's the concern, right, which is what sort of
how the גמרא Gemara explains towards the end, which I'm sorry wasn't
clear, דמסלק ליה והדר משקליה. d'misalek lei v'hadar mishkalei. That to have
taken it out during the nighttime and then to have to put
it away again, so that sort of could be the concern of
גזרת שיקוע gezeirat shiku'a that you have to store it away, you
might forget. So just better to have put it away and be
done with it rather than keep taking it back out and putting
it back again. Part of the issue here as well is we
don't exactly know how efficient this winch that they had for raising
and lowering it was.
Imagine a bronze vessel of that size full of water is probably
very, very heavy. I don't know exactly what kind of pulley system
they had at that time. I imagine it would have been a
lot of work to put it away and take it. Putting it
away is easier, you have gravity on your side. Taking it out
would be a lot of work.
Another question was was this only in בית שני? Bayit Sheni?
It's only in בית שני. Bayit Sheni. In בית ראשון Bayit Rishon
I have no idea what they did.
They have
a pulley system to bring a up when they were bargaining.
We're about to get, oh
that's
a pulley system to bring the קרבנות korbanot as well. But I
don't, they must
have had pulleys,
small, but this is also the question of block and tackle and
double pulleys and triple pulleys and things like that where you get
a mechanical advantage but then you have a lot of rope to
work with. So that's a problem. I mean I don't know when
the block and tackle was invented so I'm not sure. Charlie, you'll
have to ask you to look that up. Okay, so now we
have a bit of a new So now we have a bit
of a new question, which is going to be related to the
question of, sort of still, when did they put the כיור kiyor
away? And that's part of this question
and continuing on that line of thinking. So מתיבי, meiteivei, we have
a bit of a challenge to this discussion because now we're going
to say when did they actually put the כיור kiyor away. לא
היו רואין אותו ולא שומעין את קולו עד ששומעין קול של עץ
שעשה בן קטין מוכני לכיור והן אומרים הגיע עת קידוש ידים ורגלים
מן הכיור. Lo hayu ro'in oto velo shom'im et kolo ad sheshom'im
kol shel etz she'asa ben katin mochni lakiyor vehen omrim higi'a et
kiddush yadayim veraglayim min hakiyor. Okay.
So we have a משנה mishna in תמיד tamid that says they
would not see it and they would not hear it, I presumably
see it and hear it refers to the כיור, 搬kiyor, not 100%
sure, but they didn't see or hear the כיור 搬kiyor until they
heard the sound of the wooden crank that בן קטין Ben Katina
made for lifting the כיור. 搬kiyor. And when they would hear that
sound, they would say, oh, it's time for hand washing. So it
sounds like, okay, it sounds like what that means is they would
raise up the כיור 搬kiyor when? In the morning, right? First thing
in the morning they would take the כיור 搬kiyor out from underground
underwater and they would wash their hands, right?
So it's a bit of a problem. So let's see. So מאי
לאו דמסלק ליה, mai lav demaslek lei, does that mean that when
they were taking it out that that's when they would say that?
אלמא משקליה. alma mishkale. So
maybe you should suggest, no, it's when they were putting it away.
לאו דמשקליה. lav demishkale. אי דמשקליה, e demishkale, מי משתמע קליה? mi
mishtama kale?
So
if it's when they're putting it away, you wouldn't have heard any
sound of the crank because they could have put it away without
using the crank because to lower it would be very easy, you
could just lower it using a regular rope or regular chain or
something.
You don't want, if you do, like yeah, you don't want the
water to spill all over the place, probably easier to just use
the pulley system.
משקליה בגלגלא. meshkale begilgala. No, so they really did lower it using
the winch. So לישנא אחרינא, lishna achrina, דמשקליה בחומרתיה, demishkale bechumratei, so
they would lower it, one second,
let me see something.
Okay, so דמשקליה בחומרתיה כי היכי דלישתמע קליה. demishkale bechumratei kecheichi delishtama
kale.
I'm sorry, but wait, so we're talking about that this is the
noise that they're, so it sounds
like the question is, is this at the time
when they're, it says עת קידוש ידים ורגלים כיור. et kiddush yadayim
veraglayim kiyor. It's עת קידוש. et kiddush. Right, it should be to
use it, not to put it away.
Right, so that's the suggestion, but that's the suggestion is that maybe
what they would do is take it out, wash their hands and
feet and put it back at around sunset, right? Because the concern
is that it should be submerged for much of the night at
least, right? But that if the כהנים kohanim who started the עבודה
avoda at night need to do a new קידוש ידים ורגלים kiddush
yadayim veraglayim because according to רבי אלעזר רבי שמעון, Rabbi Elazar Rabbi
Shimon, לילה layla is מועיל לקידוש ידים ורגלים mo'il le-kiddush yadayim veraglayim
and so they would need to do a new קידוש ידים ורגלים
kiddush yadayim veraglayim then to do the עבודות avodas of the night
and they put the כיור 搬kiyor away, so at what, so that
sunset time would be a busy time around the כיור 搬kiyor because
they're putting it away but they also have to wash their hands
and feet, so it sort of, it sounds a little bit imprecise
which is why it sounds like what the משנה mishna is talking
about is in the morning, right? If you would have asked me
פשט pshat in the משנה, mishna, it sounds like it's talking about
in the morning, but they want it to be in the evening.
So that's what they're trying to, anyway. Okay.
I still don't understand, submerging it is never the time to do
קידוש ידים ורגלים. kiddush yadayim veraglayim.
No, it would be if it's for the evening.
But you're submerging it. Right. You don't submerge it to do קידוש
ידים ורגלים, kiddush yadayim veraglayim, you raise it
to do קידוש ידים ורגלים. kiddush yadayim veraglayim. Right, so they would
be submerging it right after they had used it, which is why
the לשון lashon doesn't fit. I agree. Okay. So מאי לאו דמסלק
ליה, mai lav demaslek lei, is it so you would say it's
when they're taking it out? So אלמא משקליה. alma mishkale.
לאו דמשקליה. lav demishkale. So we're talking about a case where they
were submerging it, okay. אי דמשקליה, e demishkale, if you're submerging it,
so מי משתמע קליה, mi mishtama kale, who would hear it? Because
maybe you're just lowering it on a regular rope. משקליה בגלגלא, meshkale
begilgala, so they would lower it using the wheel, so that's why
it would make noise. לישנא אחרינא, lishna achrina, a different version of
the same teaching,
דמשקליה בחומרתיה, demishkale bechumratei, they would lower it again using the crank,
the wheel that they
had, כי היכי דלישתמע קליה kecheichi delishtama kale in order to make
the
sound, ולשמעיה uleshamei so that people would hear it.
ואיתיבי, ve-aiteivei, so
right, do they really need it? והא הוה גביני כרוז, veha hava
gavini kuroz, so but don't they have גביני Gavini who was the
town crier of the בית המקדש Beis Ha-Mikdash to tell people what
time it was that they have to go wash their hands and
feet and everything?
So why would you need to make a big
noise?
בי תרי הכירי הוו עבדי. bei terei hekeirei havu avdei. They would
do a double היכר, heker, they would make a double announcement. They
would rely on the sound from the crank and they would have
a person
make... making the announcement דשמע מהאי אתי ודשמע מהאי אתי. d'shama mehai
atu v'dshama mehai atu. So everyone would be able to come whether
they heard the noise from the crank or whether they heard the
guy making the announcement. So it sounds like the conclusion is that
they wanted to try to make it so that this משנה mishna
is talking about at sunset, not at sunrise.
It's just interesting to note also that we have so much of
a, this may be a literary point, that in so much we
have this sense of שינה הכתוב בעקביו shinah hakatuv b'akeiv by קדשים
Kodshim that we have repetition of the requirement in duplicate in order
to create a sense that it's a mandatory or that it's an
obligation. So here too the גמרא Gemara is saying that in the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash they made a double announcement. When there was
an important event going on in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash they
make a double announcement to let people know. They wouldn't just rely
on a single alarm clock, they would have a double alarm clock.
And people do that also when they wake up in the morning.
If you have a snooze button, if you have an important meeting
to go to or you have a deadline, you set two alarms,
you set two warnings for yourself.
Yeah, Greek and Roman sources describe pulleys in the last century that
the temple stood.
But pulleys or block and tackle?
Basically block and tackle systems to run levers and stuff like that.
Okay so maybe, I mean it's the kind of thing that would
have been used to lift or
somebody very clever could have come up with something.
Yeah I mean
so it, a simple pulley is not going to help so much
with something that weighs 10,000 pounds or whatever but
yeah, these were fairly, apparently
they were used to produce wild stage effects in Greek theater.
Oh of course, the, right,
necessity is the mother of invention.
Yeah, the Romans were more into, were more practical than the Greeks.
The Greeks were... so it is certainly possible that it could have
been applied to lift a כיור kiyor up and down.
Well let's see, I mean it makes sense that the technology of
the time. I had a friend once in college who was an
engineer and he told me that his dream job is that when
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash is rebuilt he wants to be the
one to do the solar panels and the heating and the air
ducts and everything, he wants to be the engineer to make it
green for the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash with recycling.
I met a guy who wanted to be the computer geek who
wrote the website. Okay, this is the קרבן korban check, חטאת chatas
or he's like ordering on Amazon.
Exactly, yeah, and someone would bring the קרבן korban as your seal.
There you go,
every
reporting of the creaking sound.
They say flip the switch.
Right, because the modern one will be, you know, well-oiled machine, it's
not going to make such a... okay.
Fine. Okay, we can continue a little bit. I don't want to
get so far. Are you doing tomorrow? I'm doing tomorrow but I'm
just... it's not up to me, no, but I'm just saying I
didn't prepare so much of the next bit.
Okay, so we have a question about tomorrow which is early מנחה.
Mincha.
There's early מנחה Mincha and there's and I'm teaching half an hour
before מנחה Mincha the regular פרשה שיעור. parsha shiur. So the question
of when we would want to do the דף, daf, my assumption
had been that the דף daf would still be between מנחה Mincha
and
מעריב. Maariv. Obviously people want to go to hear Aviva Zornberg that's
totally fine as well.
I would like to have it after מנחה. Mincha.
Okay so that's fine so I think we better to keep the
normal time and if people choose to go to Aviva Zornberg I'm
not upset.
We will have about an hour and a half.
Yeah we'll have plenty of time. So maybe it's better to stop
here and we'll have a long דף daf tomorrow. I'll have better
chance to prepare it. Well it's a long דף, daf, no, but
I'm saying it takes
us to do it.
Yeah yeah of course.
What was the
story?
So good so I can go back and talk about the אילפא
Ilfa story back
to the ship.
The אילפא Ilfa story I think is the what, like תענית Taanit
דף כ daf kaf or something? Maybe I can even find it
here one second.
Some סוגיות sugyas are good to know, you know.
אילפא Ilfa תענית Taanit let's see. So one other thing, do we
want to go ahead and do the סיום siyum for נזיקין Nezikin
over שבועות Shavuot in the time we've been offered?
When was the time? סעודת הפסק Seudas hesek the last day or
something?
סעודת הפסק Seudas hesek the last day.
You know it's funny because I actually did exactly that a number
of years ago. I made a, you know, we just wanted to
do it. I did it on נזיקין Nezikin also. Yeah let's see.
תלמוד Talmud תענית. Taanit. He's in the way.
It's
a gateway,
we could wait until תשעה באב Tisha B'av to we could do
it during the nine days but you know this is ridiculous already.
We need to do it.
Well actually I have not finished הוריות. Horayot. I never did the
last דף. daf.
Oh so there you go so you were waiting.
I have been waiting yeah.
Okay here wait let me see did I find the אילפא Ilfa
סוגיא? sugya?
I mean I'm okay with, you know, like I also feel kind
of bad with not doing the Berlins but we already postponed it
once though because of.
Yeah. Where's אילפא? Ilfa? I thought he was here.
Basically the story, the story,
here let me stop the